Guide to the Moritz Schlesinger Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Moritz Schlesinger papers
1919-1973
MS 1590
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
6.5
(13 boxes)
The papers consist of correspondence, drafts, notes, reprints, newspaper clippings, and photocopies.
Schlesinger, Moritz
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Lillie Waters, 1990.
Biographical / Historical
Moritz Schlesinger was born on September 19, 1886 in Magdeburg, Germany. During World War I, he was an import merchant. Toward the end of 1918, Schlesinger served as a representative of military and civilian prisoners. From 1918 until his emigration to the United States in 1933, he was the German Foreign Ministry's expert on trade and financial relations with the Soviet Union. He died on February 10, 1974 in Washington, D.C.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The papers of Moritz Schlesinger consist of correspondence, research materials, and writings of the former German Foreign Ministry expert on economic relations between Berlin and Moscow from 1918 to 1933. The papers document the preparation of his manuscript, Erinnerungen eines Außenseiters im diplomatischen Dienst, translated as Reminiscences of an outsider in the Diplomatic Service, (earlier entitled Moritz Schlesinger: Pionier in Sowjetrussland). These memoirs trace Schlesinger's career from approximately 1918 to 1922 and the Treaty of Rapallo. Shortly before his death in 1974, Schlesinger entrusted the editing and publishing of his manuscript to Hubert Schneider. Erinnerungen was published in 1977.
With very few exceptions, the entire collection is in German. No significant attempt has been made to translate the documents. Minimal rearrangement has taken place. Original folder and binder titles have been retained.
The correspondence, incoming and outgoing with enclosures, is with family, friends, researchers, historians, professors, authors, journalists, publishers, and editors. Although some of the correspondence dates from the 1920s (the majority with Paul Scheffer, the renowned German journalist), the bulk of the correspondence files spans the 1950s-1970s when Schlesinger was corresponding with his colleagues regarding their respective writings on German-Russian relations of the post World War I era.
The research files consist of general files arranged by year and month, followed by topical files pertaining to particular subjects. Most of the general files, which parallel the chapters of his book, had been arranged chronologically (1919-1922) by Schlesinger, and this arrangement was maintained. The files consist primarily of photocopies of correspondence, memoranda, telegrams, and like material of various organizations. Those organizations most frequently represented include: Reichszentralstelle für Kriegs-und Zivilgefangene (Berlin); Auswärtiges Amt des Deutschen Reichs; Kriegsministerium; Deutsch-Russische Verhandlungen zur Rückführung der Kriegsgefangenen; Zentralkomitee der Deutschen Vereine vom Roten Kreuz; Comité International de la Croix Rouge (Genève); and Russiches Volkskommissariat für Auswärtige Angelegenheiten. Some of these photocopies bear the stamp "hergestellt im Bundesarchiv" or "Deutsches Zentralarchiv, Potsdam." Some folders include Schlesinger's fragmentary notes. Printed materials, such as newspaper and magazine clippings, complete the files.
The writings files consist primarily of drafts of Schlesinger's Erinnerungen. Loose papers found in the writings were retained in these files even though they would probably be more appropriately placed in the research files. Writings of others consist of dissertations, articles, and books written by colleagues on German-Russian relations.
Photographs of Schlesinger and unidentified persons complete the papers which were the gift of Mrs. Lilly Waters, Schlesinger's daughter, in 1990.
Germany -- Foreign relations -- Soviet Union; Germany -- History -- 1918-1933; Soviet Union -- Foreign relations -- Germany; Schlesinger, Moritz; Germany. Auswärtiges Amt
- Inventory
  - Correspondence
    - Allardt, Helmut, 1965-1972 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Altschul, Marian, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Arbeiterwohlfahrt, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Auswärtiges Amt, 1921-1924, 1933, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - B, 1956, 1963, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Becker, Walther, 1964-1973, undated (Box 1, Folder 6-12)
    - Blankenhorn, Herr, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Bonnin, Georges, 1961-1969 (Box 1, Folder 14-16)
    - Boveri, Margret, 1954-1958,1963-1970, undated (Box 1, Folder 17-23)
    - Bräutigam, Otto, 1967-1973 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Brockdorff-Rantzau, Ulrich, 1923-1928 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Büchner, [Frieda], 1962-1964 (Box 1, Folder 26-29)
    - Büchner, [Frieda], 1964-1970, undated (Box 2, Folder 30-33)
    - Büchner, Robert, 1957, 1963-1967 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Bundesarchiv, 1963-1967 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Caspari, John, 1966, 1973, undated (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Comité Central de la Croix-Rouge Suédoise, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Cornides, Wilhelm, 1964-1966 (Box 2, Folder 38)
      General note
      See also: box 1, folders 6-12
    - Deutsches Zentralarchiv, 1963-1964, undated (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Deutz, Joseph, 1968-1972 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Duckwitz, Georg, 1968-1970 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Dyck, Harvey L., 1964-1971 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Eberhard, Albert/Universitätsbuchhandlung, 1968-1972 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Ferdinand, Louis, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 43A)
    - Fischer, Professor, 1921,1963 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Forschungsinstitut der Deutschen Gesellschaft für Auswärtige Politik E.V., 1969 (Box 2, Folder 45)
      See also: box 2, folder 38
    - Frankfurter Allgemeine Zeitung, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Gatzke, Hans, 1957-1969 (Box 2, Folder 47-55)
    - H (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - Helbig, Herbert; Helbig, Ursula, 1955-1957 (Box 3, Folder 57-64)
      See also: box 3, folders 57-64
    - Hencke, Andor, 1954-1969, undated (Box 3, Folder 65-66)
    - [Juchacz?], Marie, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 67)
    - K, 1965-1968 (Box 3, Folder 68)
    - Krummacher, F. A.
      See: box 5, folder 115
    - Laubach, Ernst, 1961-1968 (Box 3, Folder 69-70)
    - Lewisohn, Nancy, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 71)
    - [Lindner], Ludovico, 1973, undated (Box 3, Folder 72)
    - Linpinsel, Eva and Eddy, 1970-1973 (Box 3, Folder 73)
    - Malanowski, Wolfgang, 1970-1972 (Box 3, Folder 74)
    - Müller, Hans Dieter, 1964-1970, undated (Box 3, Folder 75-76)
    - Müller-Werth, H., 1961 (Box 3, Folder 77)
    - [Nansen, Fridtjof], 1922-1924 (Box 3, Folder 78)
    - [Navrotskaja], Lala, undated (Box 3, Folder 79)
    - Osadczuk-Korab, B. A., 1965-1966 (Box 4, Folder 80)
    - R, 1956, 1964, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 81)
    - R. Piper & Co. Verlag, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 82)
      See also: box 3, folders 75-76
    - Riesser, Herr, 1958-1959 (Box 4, Folder 83)
    - S, 1964-1965 (Box 4, Folder 84)
    - [Saucken?], [underline], 1965, undated (Box 4, Folder 85)
    - Scheffer, Natascha, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 86)
    - Scheffer, Paul, 1922-1928 (Box 4, Folder 87-92)
    - Scheffer, Paul, 1952-1966, undated (Box 4, Folder 93-103)
    - Schneider, Hubert W., 1966-1971 (Box 4, Folder 104-105)
    - Schneider, Hubert W., 1972-1974, undated (Box 5, Folder 106)
    - Schramm, Gottfried, 1966-1974 (Box 5, Folder 107)
    - Schwedler, Anneliese, 1972-1973 (Box 5, Folder 108)
    - Volkmann, [Hans-Erich], 1962 (Box 5, Folder 109)
    - Von Dirksen, Herbert, 1927-1928 (Box 5, Folder 110)
    - [Von Swieykowski], Oda, 1972-1973 (Box 5, Folder 111)
    - W, 1956-1974 (Box 5, Folder 112)
    - Waters, Edward and Lilly, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 113)
    - Zelt, Johannes, 1966-1968 (Box 5, Folder 114)
    - Zweites Deutsches Fernsehen, 1967-1972 (Box 5, Folder 115)
    - Unidentified
      - General, 1955-1956, 1963, undated (Box 5, Folder 116)
      - "Anita", 1971-1973 (Box 5, Folder 117)
      - "Hanny", 1971-1974 (Box 5, Folder 118)
  - Research files
    - General files, 1919 (Box 5, Folder 119-130)
    - General files, 1920 (Box 6, Folder 131-142)
    - General files, 1921 January-April (Box 6, Folder 143-146)
    - General files, 1921 May-December, 1922 Apr, December (Box 7, Folder 147-156)
    - Zusammenfassung der Jahre, 1919-1933 (Box 7, Folder 157)
    - East Germany and Berlin, 1969-1971, undated (Box 7, Folder 158)
    - Rapallo, 1920-1927, 1947-1969, undated (Box 7, Folder 159-162)
    - Die Träger der Rapallo-Politik, von Herbert Helbig; reviews, clippings, correspondence, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 163)
    - Rapallo: newspaper clippings pertaining to, 1959-1966, undated (Box 7, Folder 164)
    - Riga: Konferenz des Internationalen Roten Kreuzes (1921 Jan 17), 1920-1922, undated (Box 7, Folder 165)
    - Das politische Kräfteverhältnis im Deutschen Reich auf Grund der Wahlen 1928-1933, undated (Box 7, Folder 166)
    - "Reichsregierungen 1919-1932" "Die Regierungen des Reiches", undated (Box 7, Folder 167)
    - Documents on British Foreign Policy: excerpts, 1919-1939, 1958, 1966-1971 (Box 7, Folder 168)
    - Chapters 12-13 of Schlesinger's Erinnerungen: background material, undated (Box 7, Folder 169)
    - Buchbesprechungen, 1954-1966, undated (Box 8, Folder 170-172)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1957-1974, undated (Box 8, Folder 173)
    - Lists of personal correspondence, 1919-1961 (Box 8, Folder 174)
    - Fragments, undated (Box 8, Folder 175)
  - Writings
    - Erinnerungen eines Außenseiters im diplomatischen Dienst
      - Umriß des Manuskripts der Memoiren von General a. D. M. Schlesinger, undated (Box 8, Folder 176)
      - Vorwort, 1920, 1957, 1963, undated (Box 8, Folder 177)
      - Einführung (Expl. Fischer), undated (Box 8, Folder 178)
      - Einführung (ursprünglicher Manuskript) and Belege, Material, Entwürfe zur Einführung, undated (Box 8, Folder 179)
      - Einführung Gatzke, undated (Box 8, Folder 180)
      - Einführung 3, undated (Box 8, Folder 181)
      - Kapitel I, undated (Box 8, Folder 182-183)
      - Material Kapitel I, undated (Box 8, Folder 184)
      - Ergänzungen zum Kapitel I, undated (Box 8, Folder 185)
      - Kapitel II: Arbeitsexemplar, undated (Box 9, Folder 186)
      - Material 19.1.19-28.6.19 and (Blockade) and Kapitel II, undated (Box 9, Folder 187)
      - Kapitel III: Arbeitsexemplar, undated (Box 9, Folder 188-189)
      - Kapitel IV: Entwurf, undated (Box 9, Folder 190-191)
      - Kapitel IV: Arbeitsexemplar, undated (Box 9, Folder 192-194)
      - Kapitel V/1: Entwurf, undated (Box 9, Folder 195)
      - Kapitel V/1, undated (Box 9, Folder 196)
      - Kapitel V/2, undated (Box 9, Folder 197)
      - Kapitel V/3, undated (Box 9, Folder 198)
      - Kapitel V: Arbeitsexemplar, undated (Box 10, Folder 199-201)
      - Kapitel V: überzählig, undated (Box 10, Folder 202-204)
      - Kapitel VI/1, undated (Box 10, Folder 205)
      - Kapitel VI/2, undated (Box 10, Folder 206)
      - Kapitel VI: Arbeitsexemplar, undated (Box 10, Folder 207-209)
      - Kapitel VI: pp. 65-143, undated (Box 10, Folder 210)
      - Kapitel VI: Arbeitsexemplar, duplicates and miscellaneous, undated (Box 10, Folder 211)
      - Die Tragödie [by Moritz Schlesinger?], undated (Box 10, Folder 212)
      - Various sets of loose pages found in notebooks entitled "Kapitel VI", undated (Box 10, Folder 213)
      - Bibliographische Quellen, undated (Box 10, Folder 214)
      - Early draft, undated (Box 10, Folder 215-217)
      - Revision of pp. 139-180 of early draft, undated (Box 11, Folder 218)
      - Edited copy of manuscript, undated (Box 11, Folder 219-231)
      - Erinnerungen (later draft of Erinnerungen eines Außenseiters im diplomatischen Dienst ), undated (Box 12, Folder 232-240)
    - "Der Rekord der "Novemberverbrecher", 1912-1918 (Box 12, Folder 241)
    - "Austausch der Kriegsgefangenen", undated (Box 12, Folder 242)
    - Entwürfe des deutsch-russischen Gefangenenabkommens vom 19 April 1920 and angängige Korrespondenz (faded copies), undated (Box 12, Folder 243)
    - "The Weakness of the Soviet Position Has Forced Khrushchev to Provoke a German Solution," with accompanying correspondence, 1961 (Box 12, Folder 244)
    - Handakten des Auswärtigen Amts betreffend General Konsul Schlesinger - Persönliche Korrespondenz, 1920-1923 (Box 12, Folder 245-252)
    - Fragments, undated (Box 12, Folder 253)
  - Writings of Others
    - "Das Deutsche Problem," sonntagsblatt Staats-Zeitung and Herold, I-X, 1945 October 28-December 30 (Box 13, Folder 254)
    - "The Case of Herr Scheffer," by Albert E. Kahn, 1943 (Box 13, Folder 255)
    - "Die Lehren Von Rapallo," by Paul Scheffer, 1953 (Box 13, Folder 256)
    - Weimar Germany and Soviet Russia, 1926-1933: A Study in Diplomatic Instability, by Harvey Leonard Dyck; annotated draft originally entitled A Grudging Friendship: German-Soviet Diplomatic Relations, 1926-1933
      - Part I: "Promise and Perils, 1926", undated (Box 13, Folder 257)
      - Part II: "The Anglo-Soviet Break and German-Soviet Relations,1927", undated (Box 13, Folder 258)
      - Part III: "Vanishing Illusions,1927-1929", undated (Box 13, Folder 259)
      - Part IV: "The Grand Crisis, 1929-1930", undated (Box 13, Folder 260)
      - Part V: "Revival and Decline, 1930-1938", undated (Box 13, Folder 261)
    - Deutsche Russlandpolitik in der Frühzeit der Weimarer Republik bis zum Abschluß des Rapallo-Vertrags, dissertation von Horst Günther Linke, undated (Box 13, Folder 262)
    - "Deutsche Russlandpolitik," footnotes and bibliography, undated (Box 13, Folder 263)
    - Für unsere kieinen russischen Brüder, compiled by Fridtjof Nansen, 1922 (Box 13, Folder 264)
    - Russland and die Welt, von Fridtjof Nansen, Gerhart Hauptmann, Maxim Gorki, 1922 (Box 13, Folder 265)
  - Photographs, 1928-1931, 1955, undated (Box 13, Folder 266)